Now in this lecture, we're going to discuss something known as Generative AI Security Scoping
Matrix. Now in the exam, you can expect at least one question from this topic.
Let's say you are a large organization and you have decided to build a generative
application. Now there are various ways in which you can build this application. Maybe you can
use Amazon Q, Amazon Bedrock, SageMaker, and so on. And depending on which approach you select
to build the application, there would be different security requirements. And this is what
Generative AI Security Scoping Matrix focuses on. It always calls it a mental model to classify
use cases into various scope. So as per this matrix, there are five different scope.
So scope one is the Customer app. And in Customer app, you are using a public
generative AI service. So an example of this could be Chad GPT, Amazon Party Rock, and so on.
Then you have scope two Enterprise app using an app or SaaS with generative AI features.
So an example of this is Amazon Q. And these are both by, you don't build anything,
you just buy from a third party organization. Then you have scope three where you are using
pre-trained models. So building your app on a virgin model. So Amazon Bedrock based models are an
example of scope three type of applications. Then you have scope four where using fine tune models.
So you find tune a model on your data. So an example of this is, let's say you find tune a
based model in Amazon Bedrock or you are using Amazon SageMaker Jumpstart and you find tune a
model. Then you have scope five where using self-trained model. So use Amazon SageMaker to train and
deploy a model from scratch. And all these three are cases of build and these two were by.
So what this AI security scoping matrix says is that for each scope, you will have different
kind of governance and compliance, legal and privacy, risk management, control and resilience
requirements. So now let's briefly take a look at each of the scope. So the scope one is consumer
app. In the consumer organization consumes public third party generative AI services either at
no cost or paid think of chat GPT, which is a third party generative AI service and you are either
paying a minimal fee or you are using it for free. You don't own or see the training data or
the model in this case and neither can you modify or augment it. So if you are using chat GPT,
you cannot see the training data. You cannot see the model. You cannot modify or augment it.
You just invoke the API. So you make a request and you get a response based on terms of the
service of the provider. So an example of this is an employee interacts with generative AI chat
app where public website to generate ideas for let's say upcoming marketing campaign.
Okay. Now let's look at the characteristics of scope two, which is the enterprise app.
So now for enterprise app, you use a third party enterprise application that is generative AI
features embedded think about Amazon queue. So it's a third party enterprise app and it already
has generative AI features embedded. So to use this app, you establish business relationship
between the organization and the vendor. So if you want to use Amazon queue, you have to establish
a business relationship with the AWS. So these apps will have terms and conditions that are
aimed at enterprise customers. And these are designed to offer additional protections.
And then example of this is a third party enterprise AI assistant like Amazon queue.
Then you have pre trained models and here organizations build its application using an
existing third party generative AI foundation model. And you directly integrate it with your
workload through an application programming interface or APS. So an example of this is Amazon
bedrock say you want to use a base model from Amazon bedrock. So you can make a request to these
base models from your application. And here it's a talk about an example where you can build a
rag based application using anthropic cloud. Okay. Then the fourth one is the fine tune model
where organization refines an existing third party generative AI foundation model by
fine tuning it to data specific to your business. And an example of this is we already discussed
use Amazon bedrock or SageMaker and then fine tune the model. An example of this would be
let's say you want to summarize patient records in the electronic health record. So you will
fine tune the model so that it aligns with the domain specific terminology. Then you have self-trained
models where organization builds and trains its own generative AI model from scratch using its data.
You own the data as well as the model. So an example of this may be domain specific model that you
build on Amazon SageMaker. So here is an important example as you go from scope one to five
it represents an increasing ownership for both your AI model or large language model and its
associated data. Think about this example here we have the chat GPT and here we have our own
foundation model which has been trained from scratch. So as we go from scope one to scope five
the ownership of the model as well as data will increase for the organization. So that's
something you should remember. Okay. That's pretty much it from this lecture. I'll see you in the next
lecture. Thank you.